Language: Kebanais

yoIm ol, “yoUo esim ethe mo.”
yo- Im  ol, yo- Uo    esim   ethe mo
PST-say man PST-cause wisdom sit  1SG.NOM
/jo.ˈim ol / jo.ˈuo ˈesim ˈetʰe mo/
The man said "Wisdom made me stand here."

yoUo um yosin eidela kiron kus.
yo- Uo    um      yo- sin eidela  kiron    kus.
PST-cause 3SG.NOM PST-see nothing thorough 2SG.ACC
/jo.ˈuo um jo.ˈsin eiˈdela ˈkiron kus/
It caused nothing to see you thoroughly.

Kus kum.
Kus  kum.
IMPR remember
/kus kum/
Remember it.

yoAi tiñi aloñe-so edi-tiegu, kai yotaga di aloñe um.
yo- Ai  tiñi aloñe-so  edi-ti  -egu, kai  yo- taga di  aloñe um.
PST-COP work shop -GEN NEG-stop-PART COND PST-walk ABL shop  3SG.NOM
/jo.ˈai ˈtiɲi aˈloɲeso ediˈtiegu / kai yoˈtaga di aˈloɲe um/
The shop's work was not stopped when it walked away.

yoUo um edi-youni aloñe.
yo- Uo    um      edi-yo- uni   aloñe.
PST-cause 3SG.NOM NEG-FUT-sleep shop
/jo.ˈuo um edijoˈuni aˈloɲe/
It caused the shop not to sleep (shut down).

yoAu umodo yosuñe umodo kumodo.
yo- Au  umodo   yo- suñe umodo   kumodo.
FUT-try 3PL.NOM FUT-know 3PL.NOM 3PL.ACC
/jo.ˈau uˈmodo jo.ˈsuɲe uˈmodo kuˈmodo/
They tried to know (learn) [about] them.

yoUni-da aloñe? U.
yo- Uni  -da aloñe? U.
PST-sleep-Q  shop   yes
/jo.ˈunida aˈloɲe / u/
Did the shop sleep? Yes.

yoGu um. Kai yomayemu tuñodo igu, yoUni te um.
yo- Gu um.     Kai  yo- mayemu tuñ  -odo igu, yo- Uni   te     um.
PST-do 3SG.NOM COND PST-sing   beast-PL  song PST-sleep verily 3SG.NOM
/jo.ˈgu um / kai jo.ˈmajemu ˈtuɲodo igu / jo.ˈuni te um/
It did. Because beasts sang the song, it very much slept.

yoAi aloñe edi-tiñi. Kai youoda su youni aloñe? U.
yo- Ai  aloñe edi-tiñi. Kai  yo- uo   -da su      yo- uni   aloñe? U.
PST-COP shop  NEG-work  COND PST-cause-Q  2SG.NOM PST-sleep shop   yes
/jo.ˈai aˈloɲe ediˈtiɲi / kai jo.ˈuoda su jo.ˈuni aˈloɲe / u/
The shop was not work. Because did you cause the shop to sleep? Yes.

ebMayemu mo igu, kai esim mas: ebAi reu oda.
eb- Mayemu mo      igu, kai  esim   mas:    eb- Ai  reu  oda.
FUT-sing   1SG.NOM song COND wisdom 1SG.GEN FUT-COP near evil
/ebmaˈjemu mo igu / kai ˈesim mas / eˈbai ˈreu ˈoda/
I will sing the song because of my wisdom: Evil will be near.