TEXT:

yoIm ol, “yoUo esim ethe mo.”

yoUo um yosin eidela kiron kus.

Kus kum.

yoAi tiñi aloñe-so edi-tiegu, kai yotaga di aloñe um.

yoUo um edi-youni aloñe.

yoAu umodo yosuñe umodo kumodo.

yoUni-da aloñe? U.

yoGu um. Kai yomayemu tuñodo igu, yoUni te um.

yoAi aloñe edi-tiñi. Kai youoda su youni aloñe? U.

———

BREAKDOWN:

yo-  Im  ol , “yo-  Uo    esim   ethe mo    .”
PAST-say man   PAST-cause wisdom sit  1S.NOM
man said "i caused wisdom to sit"

yo-  Uo    um     yo-  sin eidela   kiron    kus   .
PAST-cause 3S.NOM PAST-see nonsense thorough 2S.ACC
he caused you to thoroughly see nonsense

Kus kum   .
IMP 3S.ACC
him!

yo-  Ai tiñi aloñe-so  edi-ti  -egu , kai  yo-  taga di  aloñe um    .
PAST-be work store-GEN NEG-stop-PART  when PAST-walk ABL store 3S.NOM
was work of store not partially stop when he walked from store

yo-  Uo    um     edi-yo-  uni   aloñe.
PAST-cause 3S.NOM NEG-PAST-sleep store
he caused store not sleep

yo-  Au  umodo  yo-  suñe umodo kumodo .
PAST-try 3P.NOM PAST-know 3P.NOM 3P.ACC
they tried to know them

yo-  Uni  -da aloñe ? U  .
PAST-sleep-Q  store | yes
store sleep? yes

yo-  Gu um     . Kai  yo-  mayemu tuñ  -odo  igu , yo-  Uni   te             um    .
PAST-do 3S.NOM | when PAST-sing   beast-evil song  PAST-sleep very_important 3S.NOM
he did. when evil beast sang song, he slept verily

yo-  Ai aloñe edi-tiñi . Kai  yo-  uo   -da su     yo-  uni   aloñe ? U  .
PAST-be store NEG-work | when PAST-cause-Q  2S.NOM PAST-sleep store | yes
be store not work. when you caused store slept? yes

———

TRANSLATION (M):

man said "i caused wisdom to sit"
he caused you to thoroughly see nonsense
him!
was work of store not partially stop when he walked from store
he caused store not sleep
they tried to know them
store sleep? yes
he did. when evil beast sang song, he slept verily
be store not work. when you caused store slept? yes

the man said, "i caused wisdom to sit"
he caused you to see thorough nonsense
him
the storework did not partially stop when he walked away from the store
he caused the store to stop working
they tried to know them
did the store stop? yes
it did (smth). when the evil beast sang a song, it stopped verily
the store was not work. did you cause the store to stop? yes

———

TRANSLATION (OL):

ágik boógakí ke kipi hák kaeh gáʔoo
ágik kaeh keʔo keʔo ɾiʔi íge kipi
ágik ágik
kabí íge ʔapí íge ke ágik híba kabí áúʔiɾógi
ágik kaeh íge kabí
ɾiʔa ɾiʔa ʔapíkabí kipi
kuú íge kabí / gá
bíkí áúʔi / ke haɾa ɾiʔa ikɾiboógakí kaeh íge kabí
íge kabí / kuú kaeh íge kabí gá

person speech > heart i cause sit
person cause see see you no heart
person person
work no some no > person away work walk
person cause no work
people people try know
Q no work / yes
it do / > evil animal sing cause no work
no work / Q cause no work / yes